<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All the chief points contained in the Christian religion and those great truths in the word which we have not had a right apprehension for almost thirteen hundred years, never since the rise of the beast, are now discovered by the finger of God / the whole here collected into short heads, that thereby they might the better sink down into the understanding and be registred in our memories, which truths are now proved and published, by M.M.</title>
            <author>Marsin, M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35027</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14927034</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14927034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1574:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>All the chief points contained in the Christian religion and those great truths in the word which we have not had a right apprehension for almost thirteen hundred years, never since the rise of the beast, are now discovered by the finger of God / the whole here collected into short heads, that thereby they might the better sink down into the understanding and be registred in our memories, which truths are now proved and published, by M.M.</title>
                  <author>Marsin, M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by J. Clark ... E. Whitlock ... and W. Reddish ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102969:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ALL THE CHIEF POINTS Contained in the CHRISTIAN Religion, And thoſe GREAT TRUTHS in the word which we have not had a Right Apprehenſion of for almoſt Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Hundred Years, never ſince the Riſe of the Beaſt: Are now diſcovered by the FINGER of GOD. The whole here Collected into Short Heads, that thereby they might the better ſink down into the Underſtanding, and be Regiſtred in our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, which Truths are now proved and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
            <p>By M. M.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed and are to be Sold by J. <hi>Clark</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Old Change,</hi> at the upper end of <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; E. Whitlock</hi> in <hi>Stationers-Court</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner:</hi> and W. <hi>Reddiſh</hi> ni <hi>Griffiths Buildings</hi> near the <hi>Royal Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, Weſtminſter.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:102969:2"/>
            <head>The Scriptures being now Rightly Underſtood are made to agree in a Holy Harmony ſo as Juſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mercy and Truth, go hand in hand together; which before we came to have a right Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in the Word, we made to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict it ſelf, which has caus'd ſo much Diſſention amongſt us.</head>
            <p>Some there are that term the word a dead letter; but all them that believe the ſcriptures to be the word of God and take to the way directed therein, ſuch the ſcriptures are able to make wiſe unto ſalvation 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15,16 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by them we come to have faith in Chriſt Jeſus, as to believe that he will perform his promiſe according to the condition he hath made in the word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. And therefore Chriſt is ſaid to be the Author and Finiſher of Faith, becauſe he will give the hoped for promiſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to them that are found in their Obedience for the word <hi>our</hi> is not in the Hebrew Tongue.</p>
            <p>And in the Scriptures is the Wiſdom of God and the power of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſuch as walk according to that Holy rule, bleſſed are they, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>And the word being Rightly underſtood, God doth not ſwear and declare to do one thing, and abſolutely decree to do quite the contrary, for all the ſcriptures agree in one &amp; the ſame thing. <hi>And they that ſpeak not according to the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and to the Teſtimony, it is becauſe there is no Ligbt in them,</hi> Iſa. 8.20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62 8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11.</p>
            <p>And if we take to the way therein directed, God hath promiſed his aſſiſtance, and by ſo doing, we ſhall be brought off from the World, and ſo born again by having a complying frame of Spirit to the will of God, if we are to the utmoſt of our power ſincere in our endeavour.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102969:2"/>
            <head>GREAT TRUTHS in the Word are now Diſcovered, by the Finger of GOD <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Mighty God according to his Promiſe, that at <hi>Evening time it ſhould be Light,</hi> Zech. 14.7. hath now at the appointed time, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the true meaning of his word, the which we loſt the right apprehenſion of by our Predeceſſors, who were involv'd in darkneſs of Popery, whereby we are now in great miſtakes.</p>
            <p>The Truths which have not been rightly underſtood are theſe that follow,</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the Eternal Purpoſe only reacheth forward to the Eternity that lies before us, as is proved; like as Chriſt in time became the Author of Eternal Salvation, and as God in time promiſed Eternal Life.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That after <hi>Adam</hi> fell, the decree was made for the entrance into Life, to be made ſtrait; and how that ſtraitneſs doth conſiſt, is proved.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That being of old ordained to this condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath another meaning than what we have hitherto apprehended.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. In Scripture there is mention made of Three Worlds, and therefore Three Foundations, whereby it is clearly proved, there was none choſen before, or at the Foundation of the Material Heavens and Earth: and that theſe Three Worlds ſpoken of in Scripture, are Three Worlds of People. Firſt, <hi>That which ſprang from</hi> Adam. Secondly, <hi>That whichſprang from the ſeed of</hi> Noah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thirdly, <hi>That the foundation of the World to come, was laid in the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>when God brought them out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and laid them for the foundation of the World to come; and all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102969:3"/> that comes in heirs to that World, comes in as the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>and from the foundation of that World, Chriſt was figuratively ſlain in the Paſchal Lamb; and from the foundation of that World was the works of thoſe unbelieving Jews finiſhed, when they, through their unbelief, refuſed to go to fight for the Land of</hi> Canaan: <hi>And then after this their miſcarriage, God Elected and Secured a certain Remnant in Chriſt of that foundation which was then a laying in Iſrael for the world to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. It is likewiſe proved, That there was no Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thorough the old World, nor till the then time; and for <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſinfulneſs, God did Elect and make choice of the firſt Gentile Churches, and God choſe them before the body of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but not as to matter of time, but as to matter of choice and likeing in God, rather to chooſe them that had ignorantly offended him, then them that had willfully diſobeyed him, as is proved: and therefore they are ſaid to be choſen before the Foundation, which Foundation was <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. It was the Remnant choſen from among <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the firſt Gentile Churches, that had the peculiar call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for from among the Gentiles did God then Chooſe a People to the praiſe of his Name, which were choſen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſel of the will of God, for the purpoſe he had determined; which was to receive the Holy Ghoſt, &amp; to beartheir teſtimony to the Truth of the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>And alſo that in them in time to come he might ſhew forth the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Riches of his Grace.</hi> Theſe were thoſe that firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the word from the mouth of the Diſciples, and ſo believed in Chriſt thorough their word.</p>
            <p>And it was by the Example of the Elect, that all they of <hi>Macedonia</hi> &amp; <hi>Achaia</hi> believed. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4,5,6,7,8.</p>
            <p>Theſe were thoſe for whom Chriſt in a peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner prayed for, as he did not for the World; theſe were thoſe that were Glorified by their Receiving of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. for the Holy Spirit which was before but with the Diſciples, or Church, was afterward given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be in the firſt Churches: theſe were thoſe of whom St.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102969:3"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of, that were Fore-known, Called, Juſtified and Glorified, by their Receiving the Holy Ghoſt to be in them; and theſe were thoſe that were ordained to Eternal Life, being thus choſen to it who were firſt to receive the Goſpel, and who were as a candle lighted up by the Lord to enlighten the World, who lay in wickedneſs and darkneſs; and by the mighty Signs and Wonders, Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, part of the World im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Faith in the Apoſtles time, and the Word brought forth fruit in them as it did in the Elect, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>God daily added to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved;</hi> that was ſpoken to <hi>Iſrael</hi> as is proved; for of them there was ſome excluded the then offered Mercy, but by the evident witneſs of the Spirit that was given to the Elect, was the Gentile Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons convinced of the Truth of the Doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and ſo became the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> by <hi>Chrtſt,</hi> in yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their aſſent to the Obedience of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. But when the Nations came to have no love to the Truth, that they might be ſaved, but took pleaſure in Iniquity; God then gave them up to ſtrong Deluſion; that they might believe lyes, and ſo worſhip the Beaſt; for as <hi>Iſrael</hi> for ſin was left to blindneſs, ſo the Gentile Nations for ſin were left to Deluſion; for when their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers would no longer be holden with the cords of the Laws of the Lord, then did God permit them to be deceived by the Beaſt, ſo as to give their power unto him, and then did the Beaſt deprive the Nations of the Goſpel, by which God calls to his Creatures to walk in Newneſs of Life, that they may become heirs to the Promiſes.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>The Promiſe was not to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed after the Fleſh, but the ſeed in Chriſt and Iſaac was the ſeed to whom the Promiſe was made, by whom the natural ſeed of</hi> Abraham <hi>is included as well as the Adopted.</hi> But neither to the Natural Seed, nor the Adopted Seed that live after the will of the Fleſh, are they to whom the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102969:4"/> Promiſe belongs, but to them that live according to the Spirit, in Obedience to the Word, are them to whom the promiſe is made, and the promiſe is, <hi>That in time to come, God will eſtabliſh his Everlaſting Covenant with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the which crowns Life to the Soul.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>believed God and it was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> And that which <hi>Abraham</hi> believed was, that in the way of his Obedience he ſhould become heir to the Promiſes, and therefore he left his Countrey, his Kindred and his Fathers Houſe; and for the Promiſe ſake God made to <hi>Abraham, That he ſhould be the Father of many Nations;</hi> therefore when he firſt took the Gentiles into Covenant with himſelf, he did then declare his Righteouſneſs in being juſt to his Promiſe which he had made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in then Juſtifying them that believed in <hi>Jeſus.</hi> For the Gentiles believing in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that Salvation was to be had by him according to his word, which was by taking his Yoke upon them, in a willingneſs to render their ſincere Obedience to him, and thereupon they were Juſtified of God, from their paſt ſins, in and thro' Chriſt, by their willingneſs to obey him for the time to come, and the Reward promiſed was to be received both by <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, according as they ſhould afterward perform the conditions.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Whereas Chriſt ſaith, In believing that he is the Son of God, is the Rock on which he built his Church, and his Church is not only his Elect, but likewiſe all them that obey him; againſt whom the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail. <hi>For he is become the Author of Eternal Salvation to all them that obey him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Heb. 5.9. For the Faith that God requireth of us, is to believe that he is, <hi>and that he is a rewarder of them that dilligently ſeek him.</hi> Heb. 11.6. For a Believer is no longer a Believer, than he believes Salvation is to be had by Chriſt, according as he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in his word, which is, in the way of his Obedience, no more than a Righteous Man is a Righteous Man in the day that he commits Iniquity. And Good Works is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102969:4"/> proved by the word, to be a foundation for us to build our hopes of Salvation upon, as well as the Merits of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18,19. <hi>James</hi> 2.19,24 <hi>Ye ſee then, how that by Works a Man is Juſtified, and not by Faith only.</hi> For tho whoever will, is permited to come to Chriſt, yet all they that come to him muſt take his Yoke upon them, that is, Live in Obedience to him, for though Chriſt remains an Advocate with the Father for Sins of Ignorance and Sins of Infirmity, and Sins of Surprizal, yet wo be to them that willfully give themſelves a liberty to ſin Knowingly; for <hi>Iſrael</hi> was termed the Reprobate Silver; ſo likewiſe 'tis the Chriſtians that relinquiſh their Obedience is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Reprobate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the People of God's Curſe to Judgment.</p>
            <p n="12">XII<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Great Day of Salvation was, when God was in Chriſt Reconciling the World to Himſelf, which was when the Gentile Nations were firſt taken into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, he then not imputing to them their Treſpaſſes; but when they fell into Sin, and had no love to the ways of the Lord, they were then left to Deluſion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then it was not the great day of Salvation, when they were all given up to worſhip the Beaſt, but thoſe whoſe names are written in the Lambs Book of Life from the Foundation, the which were the Remnant choſen from among <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from whom the Diſciples of Chriſt ſprang, and of whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>None ſhould pluck them out of his hand;</hi> and to whom he promiſed to be with to the end of the World; and likewiſe that he would forſake none whilſt they keep the way.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Man was intruſted with the Word for his Poſterity, as <hi>Adam</hi> was with Eternal Life in Paradice for his; and God accordingly laid his commands, that they ſhould not add to the Word, nor diminiſh from it; and the Lord likewiſe annexed thoſe great Threatnings to thoſe that ſhould do either. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18,19.</p>
            <p>And the Beaſt that has deprived the Nations of the Word, by which God calls to his Creatures to walk in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102969:5"/> Newneſs of Life <hi>(and he is the Afflicter of them that would yield Obedience to it)</hi> therefore is the moſt ſevere Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance pronounced againſt him; but the Elect Remnant was ſecured by a promiſe from Chriſt, and by further pertaking of the Spirit of God, &amp; that we are none of the Remnant that are thus Elected, is as clear as the Sun in the Firmament; becauſe our Predeceſſors were all decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Beaſt, by whom the Elect Remnant were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deceived: as by the word is proved.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. VVhereas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God worketh all things after the Counſel of his own Will.</hi> The Apoſtle on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had his referrence to the great works that properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God in carrying on of Man's Redemption, and alſo in Electing ſome, and ſetting a door of Mercy open to others; and in determining that the great Glory ſhould be for the heirs of the world to come, unto whom the Election did appertain; for not only the Remnant and Firſt Churches, but <hi>Iſrael</hi> will then be the Lords E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and likewiſe all them that are found in their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though not Elected, will come in by Chriſt as heirs with them to the promiſed Reward; but the Electing or Fore-chooſing, was according to the will of God, who according to his abundant Mercy to the heirs of Promiſe, will in the time to come, eſtabliſh his Everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and theſe are the <hi>Jacob</hi> that he Loved; for <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were made the Repreſentatives of the two Worlds, <hi>Eſau</hi> of this World, and <hi>Jacob</hi> of that which is to come, as is proved; and they of this World, generally ſell their Birth-right for a meſs of Pottage, rather then they will wreſtle with an Affliction, or withſtand a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; they will part with the hope for promiſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which is the Crown of Life: and therefore God ſaid, Jacob <hi>have I Loved and</hi> Eſau <hi>have I Hated:</hi> for all are in this time to wreſtle with the Lord for the Bleſſing, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did. For tho the Election was not attained by their Willing and Running; yet the promiſed reward is to be attain'd by them that ſo doth, whether Elect or not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102969:5"/> Elect, for all that are found in their Obedience in this time, comes in as heirs to the Promiſes. But before <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> or <hi>Jacob</hi> had done Good or Evil, God only ſaid, <hi>The Elder ſhould ſerve the Younger.</hi> And this was ſo ordered by the determinate Counſel of God, that the Elder ſhould ſerve the Younger. That is, all that does not come in as the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> to be heirs to the World to come, the reſt that are then ſpared of this Elder World, <hi>or Eſau Generation,</hi> are then given as Daughters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſervants of them that are ſo, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Thus God, as the Potter, has power over his Clay to make one Veſſel to honour and another to diſhonour; but not that God did make any Veſſel to do Evil, that thereby they might become a Veſſel to Diſhonour.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. And though God ſaid, <hi>That he will ſhew Mercy on whom he will ſhew Mercy, and whom he will he hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,</hi> yet his Will is guided, as he is the fountain of all Reaſon, with greater Reaſon than we can imagin. For after God had choſen <hi>Abraham,</hi> it was then according to his obedient walking that he became heir to the Promiſes; for which Promiſe ſake, God did at the appointed time, appear to deliver <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo he will again at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time; but then for <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Cruelty and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſlavery to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God did then for his Sin harden him in unbelief, ſo as he ſhould not believe the Miracles done by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that thereby he might ſhew his power on him, by deſtroying him and his Army in the Red Sea: and therefore as in the margent of the Bible, it is ſaid, <hi>God made him ſtand.</hi> That is, Stand in the place of power that he was in, till he himſelf came in the Clouds to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him in the Sea. So likewiſe, tho God Elected ſome of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and left a door of Mercy open to others, and left others of them to Blindneſs; yet it was thoſe that were left to Blindneſs, that was moſt wicked among them, and ſuch as had the greater power to promote the knowledge of the fear of the Lord; but none of them that were found in obedient walking were left of him to Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102969:6"/> for unto them was the word of this Salvation ſent, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.26. and it is thoſe that refuſe Obedience to the ſame, that falls under the Eternal Judgment, whilſt others, that does but ignorantly offend, will be beaten with fewer ſtripes, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. And there is a Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the VVorld to come, for ſome, and none ſhall be puniſhed in that body in which they never took pleaſure to commit Iniquity. Now whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God worketh all things,</hi> the word <hi>all,</hi> in Scripture, doth not include the whole, as I have elſ-where proved.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. And God is not the author of the evil of Sin, although he is the author of the evil of Puniſhment, but upon mans repenting and returning, God hath often repented him of the Evil he thought to do unto them, as by the word is proved, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7,8,9,10. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.13,14 <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.9,10. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6,7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20,21,22,23,24. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.18,19. <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.6. <hi>I am weary with Repenting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas God ſaith Mal 3.6. <hi>I am the Lord I Change not,</hi> This God ſpake as to his Attributes, as his Juſtice, Mercy and Truth in which he is an Unchangable Being, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for his promiſe ſake it is, that the Sons of <hi>Jacob</hi> are not conſumed; for in time to come they are to inherit the Land.</p>
            <p>But when God promiſeth a Bleſſing without condition, then he Repenteth not, <hi>For God is not a man that he ſhould Lye, neither the Son of Man that be ſhould Repent: Hath be ſaid, and ſhall he not do it? or hath he ſpoken and ſhall he not make it good? for God hath promiſed to Bleſs Iſrael, and they ſhall be Bleſſed; and then will he behold no Iniquity in Jacob, when be hath purged all Iniquity from them.</hi> For both in the Old and New Teſtament, thoſe things which are to come, are mentioned, as though they were already paſt, or preſent; ſo accordingly St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating about the Covenant, ſometimes expreſſeth himſelf as though it were already done, that is, Eſtabliſht; but by the whole ſcope of his words he doth fully declare to the contrary, but that they were then given the Holy Ghoſt, which did bear witneſs with their Spirit, they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102969:6"/> they were choſen to be heirs of that promiſed Covenant; but if they did again willfully Sin, and ſo do deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, then there remained for them no more ſacrifice for Sin, but a fearful looking for of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and fiery Indignation; for if they ſinned wilfully under the greater Light, they fell under the greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: for although among the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were the Remnant that was ſecured by a promiſe from Chriſt, <hi>that none ſhould pluck them out of his hand;</hi> but they ſtood not by the eſtabliſhing of the Everlaſting Covenant, but by a promiſe from Chriſt, that they ſhould not only be heirs to it, but inheritors of it; and when the Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renant is Eſtabliſhed, then by that Covenant, Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſecured as well to the Body as the Soul; for then the Souls of the Raiſed Saints will be again United to their Bodies, and bleſſed in them; and ſo <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the True Believers, will not only then by that Covenant, have an Inherent Perfect Righteouſueſs, but they will then be freed from Sickneſs, Sorrow, Want, and the troubles that are now in this Life, and in the time to come, in which God will manifeſt his power, he will then alſo make his People <hi>Iſrael</hi> a willing People; &amp; then it is he will eſtabliſh his Everlaſting Covenant with them, for the good of them and their Children after them. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. For this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Covenant was to be eſtabliſhed with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed together in their Generation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7,8. And when the Lord again comes to Reſtore all things, he will then make Mount Sion an Eternal Excellency, and the Joy of many Generations; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.15. And then not only the Remnant, but likewiſe the body of the Natural Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> will then be the Lords Elect, which he will gather from the four winds into which he hath driven them.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. The Chriſtians of the Gentile Race, that comes in by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> were all termed hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in the Old Teſtament, as is proved: ſo as the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere ſtroke threatned in the Goſpel, will fall on the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that ſhall be found in Rebellion and Darkneſs at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102969:7"/> that day, for the Law and Goſpel ſpeak but to them that are under it; therefore they are the World that will be condemned by it, that will not live in Obedience to it; <hi>Iſrael</hi> is not reckoned with the World, therefore the Lord ordered Proclamation to be made to the end of the world, <hi>Say ye to the daughter of Sion, Behold thy Salvation cometh, behold his Reward is with him,</hi> Iſa. 62.11. Thereby ſhewing the power of this world will be taken away when their Salvation cometh.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. In the Word there is mention made of Three Evers, Three Times, Three Generations, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſaid, he would come before this Generation paſſeth away; and the Three Worlds ſpoken of, is the old World, this World, and the World to come, unto whom the Bleſſing is promiſed of the eſtabliſhing the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, which crowns Life to the Soul, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Raiſed Saints, but to Iſrael and all that long for his Appearing, and according to his Word, in an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent frame wait for him. Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth <hi>To lay up in ſtore a good foundation againſt the time to come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1 Tim. 6.19.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. There is likewiſe figarative Heavens and Earth ſpoken of in ſcripture. And the Lord, becauſe of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels</hi> ſinfulneſs, for which they were left to blindneſs; he therefore ſpake to them in parables, all theſe things being now at the appointed time rightly underſtood, it turns the ſcene, whereby the Viſion of the coming of the Lord is made ſo plain, that he that runs may read it.</p>
            <p>And when the Lord comes, the true Chriſtian will be gathered as the Lord hath declared, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> will then be gathered according as God by his Prophets to them hath revealed, whoſe teſtimony they have received and then will the Lord gather in others with them.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. And now the Lord according to his word, that at the end of the time, knowledge ſhould be increaſed <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4. <hi>And that at evening time it ſhhould<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be light</hi> Zach. 14.4. <hi>And that at the end of the time the Viſion ſhould ſpeak</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102969:7"/> Hab. 2.3. Hath now made his promiſe, good in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the great and hidden myſteries, in his word, which we have not rightly underſtood, are now made ſo plain that there is no more room for Miſtake, and by a ſpeedy Reformation, and owning the whole Truth, we may not only ſave our ſelves, but thereby, great part of the Chriſtian World may be awakened to come out from the Darkneſs which they are now under.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. And it is ſaid, <hi>How ſhall a Young man Cleanſe his way. But by taking heed thereto, according to the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which is a Light to the Path, and Lanthorn to the Feet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by which he calls to us to amend our lives. And the like is ſaid in the New Teſtament. <hi>He that looketh into the perfect Law of liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a forgetfull hearer, but a doer of the work, this is the man that ſhall be Bleſſed in his deeds,</hi> James 1.25. And in that it is termed the perfect Law, is becauſe it is a perfect and upright rule, by which we are to walk, and the Law of liberty, becauſe upon the wills conſenting to yield ſincere obedience to all Gods Commands and Preceps, ſuch are thereby ſet clear at liberty from the condemning power of their paſt ſins, and ſhall be Bleſſed in the promiſed reward if they be not forgetfull hearers, but doers of the work, And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the Heathen, <hi>God is not far from every one</hi> Acts 17.27,28. And to them to whom God hath given his word, he hath promiſed that they that Seek him ſhall find him if they ſearch for him with the whole heart, &amp; Chriſt ſaith, <hi>VVho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will let him come.</hi> And tho we can do nothing without Gods aſſiſtance, <hi>for in him we live, move, &amp; have our being,</hi> &amp; it is he that hath laid the Spiritual meat before us, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11.4. whereby to guide our feet into the way of peace, hath promiſed, that whilſt they keep the way, he will be with them. And the Prodigal that knew that he had wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from his fathers Houſe, firſt lookt home before his father lookt on him; and tho God may ſome times go out of his ordinary way of working, and pluck as it were a brand out of the burning, yet he no longer ſecurely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102969:8"/> ſtands then he is found in his obedience, for it is thoſe that will fall under the condemnation that will not chooſe the fear of the Lord <hi>Prov</hi> 1.29. but for thoſe that thro long continuance in ſin, have ſeared their Conſcience, whereby they become left of God to a ſtupid ſenſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is ſuch cannot learn to do well, no more then the Ethiopian can change his Skin <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but whilſt we have a ſenſe to ſee the evil inclinations which our natures are prone to, we may continually pray, <hi>Lord turn thou us, and we ſhall be turned.</hi> And if man does his endeavour, God will never be wanting to ſuch <hi>And if we reſiſt the devil he will flee from us, And if we draw nigh to God he will draw nigh to us</hi> James 4.7,8.</p>
            <p>But whereas the Lord ſaith, <hi>No man can come to me except the Father draw him:</hi> And the drawings of God are the tenders of his Grace, with the good motions of his Spirit, and checks of Conſcience, the which the old World and <hi>Iſrael</hi> had, till they reſiſted, for which they were condemned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Lord ſaith, <hi>Except a Man be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain he cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> This was ſpoken to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> who had embraced this preſent World, and therefore came to Jeſus by Night, as being aſhamed to own him; and ſuch are to be born again, or brought off from the World, or they cannot enter into the kingdom of Heaven, as is more fully proved in the book where the Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> is fully explained, and alſo there in is made appear, what is meant by the Wind blowing where it liſteth; and likewiſe therein is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Who they are that are not under the condemning power of the Law for their paſt ſins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Grace; that they are ſuch as will and do walk in Newneſs of Life; and if we will enter into Life, we muſt keep the Commandments, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17. <hi>For all are his ſervants to whom ye obey, whether of ſin unto death, or of Obedience unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 6.16.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>It is not for the works of Righteouſneſs that we have done, but of his Mercy be ſaved us.</hi> This was ſpoken of the Elect who were then brought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102969:8"/> out of Idolatry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and has no reference to us, as is proved.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. Whereas the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Ye are ſaved by Grace, &amp; not of works.</hi> that is, Man could not perform good works to that perfection as to become juſtified by them without the Merits of Chriſt, and therefore ſaved by Grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but there is none that live in the performance of good works, but ſhall be rewarded according to their works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12.</p>
            <p>The Eternal Life that is now in this time given the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, excepting the very elect, which is the ſtanding wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is no otherwiſe given, then it was to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> for had they never ſinned, they ſhould never have dyed; ſo the true Believer that believes ſalvation is to be had in the way of his obedience according to the word of the Lord, he ſhall never be caſt off, but the Man that Departs from the Lord by wilful committing Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he is no longer a Believer according to the Goſpel, as is proved.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. Whereas the Lord ſaid, when he ſent his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples forth to preach the Goſpel to all the World, <hi>He that believeth ſhall be ſaved, and he that believeth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark 16.15,16,17. That is, He that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Doctrine that he ſent them forth to Teach; and the Mercy and Condemnation, was to them that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly Believed, or refuſed Believing the ſame, as not to obey the truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19,20. For the Lord ſpeaks by the Law and Goſpel but to them that hears it, as proved. But whereas Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He that Believeth not is condemned already,</hi> This the Lord ſpake to the Jews, who had heard him, but believed not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were condemned: and thereby it alſo ſheweth, that more of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might have been ſaved, had they been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take hold of the offered Mercy.</p>
            <p>I here gather ſo many heads together, that thro' the miſinterpretation of the Scriptures, Satan might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile ſo many of their Souls; for if we take a text of Scripture as it ſtands alone, without weighing how it is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102969:9"/> ſpoken, and what the whole ſcope of the Scripture tends to, we may raiſe as falce Doctrine as God is True.</p>
            <p>O God who of thy great Mercy hath made thy word plain in thoſe things we have been miſtaken in, give more of thy Aſſiſting Grace, for to improve the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth.</p>
            <p>Theſe things which are here but hinted, with the other diſputable places, and alſo the ſigns of the Times, with the near approach of the coming of the Lord, are now fully explained and proved in about four ſmall Treatiſes</p>
            <p>The Books contain ſo many ſeveral heads that I have not here room to incert them, but by them the word is ſo plain, that none need any longer remain in miſtakes, that are willing to underſtand the Truth. I ſhall only here mention the chief Title of each Book. Firſt, The Explaination of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Price bound 10.<hi>d.</hi> bound up with the Chriſtian Belief, which has the Eexplanation of the Trinity <hi>Price</hi> 1<hi>s.</hi> 2<hi>d.</hi> The ſigns of the times, and coming of the Lord, bound up with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Moſes</hi> that foretold the firing of the Mountains, <hi>Price</hi> bound 10<hi>d.</hi> all three bound up togather. <hi>Price</hi> 1<hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi> The book that Proveth there Worlds and three Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations with the Tree of knowledge of good and evil, <hi>Price</hi> bound 1<hi>s.</hi> And are to be Sold at the places before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Title. The book of the Figurative Speeches is not yet out.</p>
            <p>My aim is at the good of Souls, and therefore th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they that underſtand not the word may be convinced o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Truth. I Refer my Books to the Lord Biſhops<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who I believe are men of that integrity that will not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Truth, to whom I ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance give further ſatisfaction if required; and when God had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned my underſtanding in his word, I did dare do no other then leave and venture the little concern I had, and come above a Hundred Miles to acquaint the Nation, what God is a going about to do; this being the little time that is given the Chriſtians to prepare.</p>
            <closer>God make our KING and Parliament inſtruments for his Glory.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
